We'll call it the regular meeting among City Council from Monday, May 16, 2022, to public input and unscheduled personal premises.
Have none?
Three, consent agenda staff recommends we approve on its four and five.
Mayor Parker.
Oh.
Public input?
Yep.
Thank you, ladies and gentlemen.
My name is Cramer.
I live on 23rd Avenue Southwest, bottom of the hill in the morning edition.
And two weeks we've been on that street in that house for 50 years.
We have a little problem with our street.
We had problems with streets elsewhere, of course.
But this particular problem brought the street department out last fall to deal with it and they dug it up.
Not sure that they found anything but covered it up after going down about four feet or so.
And naturally has to settle throughout the winter spring.
And we've had another rain and we have another, of course, the trucks that pick up the trash to settle it down.
It's ready now to be dealt with and I'm sure the city is going to be doing some street work in the future.
The problem that we have here is there's considerable amount of drainage coming out of that area.
And it has a bad color, has a bad oil to it.
It's completely ruined the front of my concrete driveway and my neighbors down line.
I unfortunately had to give this same story to a couple of gentlemen in the room here to see me and one of them said that he would make certain.
I said this long to street department and someone would reach out to me.
Unfortunately, there are just hasn't been long enough to touch me yet.
And I didn't hear anything from them.
I'm simply here to point out this problem to you.
What's coming out of there?
We've made Tore Creek look like a trout stream.
EPA would not like this at all.
And so I'm sure that the city will, someone here.
I would be serving the pets, take you care of and I appreciate your ties,
I appreciate to listen to me, thank you for your service, all of you.
Thank you.
Mr. Primer, what was your first name?
Primer.
And your first name?
Oh, I know.
Oh, me.
Thank you.
For what?
Three.
And that recommends we approve our four and five.
Just go move.
Second.
Double.
High.
East step.
Five.
Simmer.
Of state.
Davis.
Aye.
Farther.
High.
Seize.
Bugs and amendment.
Number 22-25 grants.
Police department.
And 22-26 grant for streets.
stadium and utility approved.
All right, thank you.
You can matter.
Do a 225 first, I can 18, 19, but please go a few donations that were put into the grant fund in 1920.
They got a $10,000 grant and it's been all over because $177 left in the grant fund.
There is a police fund that that money would be better served in.
So this allowed us to move up money from the grant fund to the police fund.
So the police can spend it for the rest of the money.
And that's been $177 by itself.
Out of the grant fund.
It's for clarification.
He's talking about fiscal years 18 and 19 and not 18, 19.
And fiscal years 19 and 20 and not 19, 20.
That is all years.
Do you need these approved separately or?
I believe so.
Okay.
That's the same for ready to go.
I'd like to go.
Parker.
Davis.
Sunberg.
That.
Double.
All right.
Twenty.
Six.
The first part of that is given the fire department to build in stand or cigarette fundraising money.
The second part of that is each year.
We got three bonds.
We budget.
Agent fees for somebody take care of bonds for us.
We underestimate it.
Those agencies.
Those years.
That's allowed us to finish.
I know.
So on the fire department for the truck.
So the cigarette.
What did we get set up for?
The 11,111 is what they perceive today.
That was it directly to a defensive count that they can stand.
Who want to do the proper procedures of person policy.
Proper.
Is that where you go?
Is that good with all of them?
Everybody.
So they'll be able to spend that money before it comes here for approval?
Yes.
Okay.
I'll give it a little bit.
Thank you.
All right.
Be staffed.
Thank you.
So in the least agreement with the town of Farland,
to Lisa, 2014, for explore from the city of Miami.
We have this our old can in car.
There's no car, can I can where we went to, why not?
And ask to take this can on where they, and we can, we can do what the town, why not?
To tell that I have to do that.
The car, because of the specializing equipment that happened to vehicle, can't be used as a normal place car.
It's fully capable to kind of on the back.
Everything is stuck.
It goes the back.
And it's been no real product because it smells like can.
Right now, it's a lot of riding the ground.
It's got a flat tire and a dead battery.
Which can have to be prepared for some barriers.
So, she's done.
Fairly and just that.
And the ability to do can and they don't have a vehicle that's equipped.
As opposed, it's been the 2030 global $40,000 for just a cage.
And we told them we would entertain possibly released with their doorways and just give them a car.
It's a 2014 Ford.
That should be, thanks to the wreckwise and come back together.
I don't know if we could cage out of it because the way it's been.
To be clear, it was scheduled to be replaced before.
Yes, yes, it was.
In fact, we had the budget.
So this year, a new canine vehicle.
Two surplus that vehicle.
So it was definitely beyond our service line for what we need.
So we get another canine?
No.
We're not.
Not in the future.
I didn't see that in our future anywhere close.
I can't have broken quite honestly.
It's just very expensive.
And there's agencies all around.
How long did we hear at our 12,000?
You know, the dog itself is $1,000.
And almost 40 hours a month.
Special training just with the dog.
And we did.
Probably we've done optimations.
And the last year or so.
And it was expensive probably.
The great tool.
But I blasted up.
We levered up.
But we're currently funding.
I think there's better ways we can spend our money to the new dog.
What would be the length of this lease?
What's the length of the lease?
I'm telling you, I don't know that we have a...
I think it was in perpetuity until they knew what we needed it.
Darryard?
No, our year.
Okay, perfect.
And we've done this several times.
We've given guinea O'Cars, we've given guinea O'Cars.
We've given guinea O'Cars, we've...
Not in contact with Rax, we're trying to help other agencies,
but with stuff like that.
Having the trail and services available
that we do, we generally don't have any problems getting someone to...
to donate K9 usage for us when needed.
Yeah.
We'll make a motion we approve.
Let's take it.
Are you deaf?
I'm deaf?
I'm deaf.
I'm a ...
We're trying to see if we could say cost of paying for a new machine on the lease agreement for them.
But that machine is 10 years old.
It's kind of outlived its life and they can no longer get parts for it.
So what I'm asking is to approve this amendment to add one device to replace the current one to keep the term limits.
To 40 months rather than side to do lease, which is 60 that way.
In 40 months when we do come around to looking at fitting out replacements.
We can do it all at once rather than have one or two outliers.
Oh my promotion.
Second.
Simple.
E step.
Senator.
Hi.
Davis.
Parker.
Hi.
Thank you.
9.
Resolution CC.
22 days.
06 authorizing acceptance of the coronavirus local fiscal recovery funds for non-antival
units of government, ARPA, creation of the necessary budget amendments and execution
of all required funding documents.
Jill.
So, this is really a housekeeping matter and how you are planning to use your ARPA
money.
So far, or we are going to, the city is going to receive 2,885,888 dollars of
glue once it's total.
Right now we've received half of that.
We expect the second half to come in September.
This resolution actually has the city declaring its attention to use the $10,000
revenue loss standard allowance category.
And using that category does 2 things, 1, it simplifies the requirements for recording.
And it also allows us to use the government, and I'm using this because they used it,
the government service definition, which included in that definition is to be able to use your
ARPA money for real repair.
And as you know, during our budget sessions, our budget includes 250,000 for water distribution
improvements of the ARPA money, and then the rest of the $2 million and $2,000,000,
$2,000 by thousands of change will be used for road repair.
And of course that's not all that's been used for that.
So you're saying this will be an extra 2 million for road repair.
Yes.
Okay.
If you've heard of this, I'll make a motion to approve that.
And I'll second it.
Parker.
Hi.
Davis.
Thank you.
10.
Load on recommendation from the City of Zelene and Planning Commission.
The Resonum property located at 2128 B. Northwest from a planned unit development to a general
commercial approved ordinance 2022.
That's 08 amending the zoning map.
Yeah.
So this is a property that is southwest of Bethany Christian Church of 22nd.
And it resumed a planned unit development a couple of years ago.
They did some medical marijuana business associated with it.
And now they're selling it.
Actually, they were going to sell it and it was like it's going to get
a minute.
And they need to have that resumed commercial, general commercial.
The last I heard it's going to be a 24 hour daycare service, which is beneficial to our community.
So city zoning and planning commission approved the recommendation to have it.
That's where I'm behind the church, not a lot.
Yeah, it's not.
But it's the church.
It needs to be like an assisted living place, correct?
It needs to be a living facility.
Yeah.
Was it zone commercial, then?
It was commercial, originally.
I said on a board at that church, where the ones that sold it actually, and it never
was commercial as long as we owned it.
But then when we sold it to the nursing center behind us, then they...
I think this was all together, and then the house, the separate now from the species.
It was all that whole lot of all together yet, because at one time, that was a part of...
So zoning is just for this.
It doesn't affect this, this lock that means right there.
Okay.
And we did have a public hearing that there was no one else present to a person.
Sounds like a co-concept, it gives some co-op to work nights.
Yeah, I know that.
Can we group a child?
When I worked in the manufacturing world, we had big-guide shifts, and there was always
a week for child care.
Mike emotion.
Thank you.
Double.
Hi.
Submerk.
Davis.
Staying.
You step.
Parker.
Hi.
Then 11 is the same property, 2022-08, the zoning map, the emergency clause to amend the zoning
map.
The zoning in 2021-28 means we're blessed to plan unit development to general, commercial.
I'll make a motion.
Second.
Okay.
Perfect.
Thanks, Submerk.
Thank you.
Davis.
Staying.
You step.
12.
Letter of support from the City of Mio, for a Department of Commerce Emergency Solutions
Grant for the Grand Lake Mental Health Center.
So Mayor members of the Council, I met with Cassie Conran, and Grand Lake Mental Health, a
week and a half ago, and she had robbed this to my attention that they were seeking just
letters of support for their application, for this emergency solutions grant, through the Department
of Corrections.
This grant would allow them funding to be able to help homeless or those facing their homelessness
to get temporary shelter.
And to those they provide mental health services to, and they do do that in this.
and so they are a partner of which is under good administration and really seeking to work closely with the city.
And I've had multiple productive meetings with them, and I just would encourage you to consider very quest for this letter of support.
There are no financial ties with this letter.
Great motion, we approve.
Second.
Estep.
Thank you.
Senator.
Hi.
Dr. Goldstein.
13 award bid C22-12 in amount of $12,757 dollars to constitution.
Construction of the demolition of 1030 E-South West.
Approved contract contingent upon the submission of required contract documents.
And a pretty city manager or his designated need to sign notice to proceed.
So this is part of the FEMA acquisition grant.
This is one of three commercial properties.
The address for this property is 1030 E-South West.
We got, and you guys had all the bids that were submitted in the packets.
We got, I think it was homework.
Bids that were open last Friday in college came in with the list.
Hey, Christy.
With, I went, when those got emailed to us, I went through all the mid packets.
And there's such a, I guess I need some clarification because there's,
they're all over the map from lowest to highest.
From lowest to highest, there's $126,000 difference.
I started going through some things and looking.
And I'm really not sure that our lowest bid caught everything that was in there.
So what are your guidelines as far as change orders going to be to this?
Because the way I'm looking at this is a bid as a bid.
And the second thing is who's going to be overseen making sure that all the foundations,
on 18 inches is dug down, 18 inches is brought back in.
With the cost of dirt right now, there's $10,000 in dirt.
And so I'm just trying to figure out how columns construction captured everything in the bid packet at $12,000.
I understand what you're saying, and there is quite a bit of difference between the bids.
And all this has been, we go out to bid on every demo that we do, and he always comes in.
The list there have been maybe two or three in the past that I've had to call in asking to come back and do more field work because it wasn't level or something was wrong and it's always come back and did that work for us.
I'm the project manager over the project so I'll have oversight on it and our department will be dealing with the inspections on it.
We're going to be queueing on the tape removal for one of the commercial properties that he'll have to get a bond.
He'll get a conditional award that he's been submitting to all of his paperwork and part of that paperwork that's to get a bond.
The performance bond, the bid bond.
My experience with bond companies when they see them because they'll get all four of these numbers the bonding company will to see where they're at.
And they could be a little gun shy with.
I'm just want to make sure that there's no change orders that are going to roll through on this thing that he missed out on 30 or 40 thousand dollars worth of work.
I completely agree with what you're saying. I can't.
There shouldn't be any change orders that I can guarantee that he won't try to do a change order.
I've never had that in my experience.
What's the process for change orders and something like this does that come for approval through?
It would have to, especially because it's a grant.
It would have to come back to you guys.
So, change laws that run the change order limits at a 10 percent.
So, if there were a change order that it would have seen 10 percent of the total cost that was bid, we would shut it down and we bid.
So, there would not be an excessive change order that would place them anywhere near a false point of peace.
It would have been twice as long as you think it's that.
So, if there was a change order to come over $1275, then the project would get shut down.
We would bid.
Because that's what the law sets is that for the very reason we can talk about.
So, it will look at excessive additional costs.
I've seen it bid twice the project.
We're going to shut it down and we bid.
And also, you know, I just need to say that it is.
contract with new diligence. We need to do more to know how to place a bid. We have to
have that. You place the base on that. Right. You're going to get those bonds. You want me
to have things going to, because you don't have faith in it or not. So, when we do everything
we can do to protect that tax all of them that we're going to spend. Almost definitely,
only concern was they were so outrageous. I mean, there are such big gaps in between one
and two and three and four. And we did complete ask the questions we need to ask you
order with new confidence in their beds if you feel like we need to. He might have a source
for his soil. It doesn't cost him any. We don't need to know that. Right. Thank you.
Christy, you said he worked with him before. As his beds came in low like this before compared to
others. Yeah. Always. Always. Is there any ground food fuel tanks there? Yes, but that's a different
that's going to get been separate. And it's under the supervision of the team. It'll be coming back to you guys.
Okay. But it's done. We have special contractors. We have to sit in that too. They still want the
crew of press crews and they have aSOIT. This is just a building, right?
Building some parking workers. Entering down nation slabs.огда.
Any other questions for Christine.
That's myself.
Hi.
You step gras.
14, who were a bit of CC 22-13 amount of $1,995 to college construction for demolition of 1130 East Southwest,
proved contract continued upon the submission of required document contract documents and approved city manager,
or has it designated me to sign notice to proceed.
So 13 was the old big daddy's right.
12 is for Jan's. This is 13.
13 is for students.
You said 12?
13's big daddy's 14.
Do I have an opposite?
14 is 14.
Okay.
14 is 30.
Now 14 is the Thunderbird.
No, that's 15.
14 is 30.
I'm sorry.
I'm looking at the I apologize.
I'm looking at the bid numbers.
Which is 12.
14.
10, 10, 30.
Yes, I apologize.
11, 30.
Yes.
Any questions for Chris Del Allen?
I'll make you a proof.
Second.
East End.
Don't go.
Hi.
Center.
Davis.
Hi.
Parker.
15.
22.
Dash 14.
27,000.
$240 to college construction.
But the demolition of 1603 East, Steve O'Neill's Boulevard.
The proof contract takes you upon the submission of a required contract documents.
And for city managers, doesn't need to sign those to proceed.
But this was a Thunderbird.
Yes.
I'll ask Melissa to correspond to you.
Do that.
I don't know.
I'll make a motion to approve.
Second.
Parker.
East End.
Davis.
Hi.
Center.
Double.
All right.
Thank you.
16.
Another new business of any, which is a residence of the posting of this agenda.
17.
Staff reports.
18.
Mayor and Council of Community Announcements.
And I would like to reaffirm my commitment to academic development that I may
rise running for this seat.
I will not.
I will not put myself in position to give one person exclusive rights over another to a certain thing.
To a certain business, a certain opportunity.
So that was brought to me.
And it was something that I couldn't and shouldn't have done.
So I told the person, I couldn't do that.
And return it hurt a local contractor, which was definitely not my intention.
or my want ever, but that commitment, I felt like it was the right thing to do in my conversation
with that business and I would have that exact same conversation again because I just don't
think we can put ourselves in that position as a community.
I'll be brief, I had an occasion to visit with the right hand of the owner of Pete's
Court after that incident of place and his comment was very telling and very direct because
that's just who they are.
He said David, the mayor was doing what the mayor should have done.
The question had been asked if a tunnel had been kicked around or discussed in my
Emma that answers from as I understood it through him from the mayor back to the contractor
or the man with car wash was yes and didn't know what the future held for that individual
but it had happened.
But the devil is always in the details, I mean people leave out sensational items that
become important.
Come to find out two or three months, three or four months prior this gentleman and I hate
that for him had spent serious money and four stock cans as a town less than half our size
and had a tunnel move in on him, which drastically affected his investment.
So there was already a sense of concern and a little bit of paranoia about tunnels when
that conversation occurred and I just wanted folks to know that.
That came from Kevin Cole or really cool dude is out in the field for Pete's Court and
I just called because they've been such great partners of the community.
I've spent serious money here and one of the share of the details with you because I thought
they were omitted at a Facebook sharing.
of said account, since Councilman Davis touched on that subject, that wasn't going to say anything
on the subject, just because the company affected is the company I've worked for for 25 years.
So I really didn't feel that I should be addressing it up here, but I'm going to.
The car wash was coming in, and David is correct, Kyle did have, which Kyle's the builder.
He did have that happened to him in Fort Scott.
He put in the really nice car wash, and then a few months later, tunnel moved in.
But as far as a minor project goes, he had already ordered the equipment, put the deposit
down, the equipment's ready to be picked up today, actually had a conversation with him yesterday,
and I don't know if he's going to get his deposit back on that.
But Mayor Parker is also correct in the conversation that he had with Kyle, Kyle asked him
bless for them not to pursue another car wash to come in, you know, bless could guarantee it.
But a lot of the conversation that's happened has been twisted and turned and thrown out their own
Facebook, but the reason the car wash is not coming in is the conversation that the builder
had with the mayor.
I mean, that's point, like, intentional, not intentional.
I can't speak for bless, you know, I can't speak for Kyle, I was not there during the conversation.
I just know why we were told to cease production on the car wash.
And it up, keep the rock clear, catered off, open up the rest of the concrete, don't
take it off, have your equipment gone and be done.
I tend to believe the guy that gave us the work for the reasons of why he's telling us to shut
it down.
I'm personally not mad at anybody, you know, things happen, conversations happen.
I think all of us as a council in the mayor need to pick our words wisely in the conversations
we have with people and realize what conversation you're going to have is going to affect
to and where in your town, not only did it affect the local business that's been a business
in my life for over 30 years.
But it also affected a lot of other things in town revenue till the revenue is coming in
All the stuff on Facebook. I refuse to get on there in comment and get it to an argument with somebody
It's not worth my time
You know people sitting out there you your children, whoever
It don't make them look good
And it just don't you know people sit there in Bash the city all the time
Her bash us for what we do or what we vote on and I can honestly say the way I vote
I vote with my heart and what makes sense if it don't make sense
I'm not gonna vote to approve it whether these gentlemen up here do or don't but
That's what I believe why the car washes not going on
I mean I could have written statements from the builder of why I
Could probably go back and text messages just between him and my build it or my company
I'm not gonna give you guys all of that
But since these two gentlemen touched on that
I felt like I needed to say something myself and I'll say
Can't count for the mayor. I would
Respectfully recommend that we're off the edge of the attention
We're gonna need to die in one announcements and I would suggest that if you're free to say anything
You want to after the meetings that you're on but I would not do this at this time
Okay, so I'm not saying matters me big
All right, thank you all
Pulls gonna be opening on May 28. Hey there's a positive that's fantastic. We've had
Some number of applicants, but obviously still looking for lifeguards, so please please
Anyone that knows anyone interested in doing lifeguards
Please send them our way in the Roy's looking for folks to get out there and get fully staffed
Obviously and everybody compared before May 28
Also want to do announced the Northeast Oklahoma softball craze tournament will be May 21st or 22nd
This is a sanctioned USSA fast-pitched off-long tournament
We're anticipating about 30 teams
So under we'll get back up to our dead-scale turns. This is so
This is a brain free 21st and 22nd so this week can rain free everybody across the fingers
We'll have to run a rain pass all the trucks doing the rain dance
We hope to see all of our restaurants school and gas stations busy lots of activity going on in town
So that's a real positive thing
Don't forget the farmers market is now open as of last week. I got to go out there and kind of see
opening evening and got me and we go to the flat strawberries which was fantastic.
If you get a chance, please get out there and check it out.
It's now out of your fairgrounds and growing every day.
It's really neat.
They're doing a big mural on the back wall.
That an artist is doing on the bathrooms.
They're back there and not on the sidewalk.
Which obviously is a historic building.
But the bathrooms in the back, they are.
It's going to be really cool.
I also wanted to commend the library on a great book sale.
They ran this past weekend.
They had over $500 and had lots of people out.
Greg turned out on Saturday.
And wanted to commend some of you Smith with the library who received her public library
and certification.
Congratulations for her continuing to move or folks forward.
And that has been all I had for him.
Thank you.
Spice better.
Did open.
Oh gosh.
They've been doing the testing on it.
DQ is going to be out and doing some final testing.
I think Kevin told me they were still coordinating with DQ for the local testing out there.
Kind of room in the day.
So I'll have to get it to you.
Right.
23.
Hopefully.
Hopefully we're going to get the testing wrap.
What is this for?
Okay.
I'll tell you in the swings.
Here's how I go by there.
It's funny when I went by there.
My wife drove down there the other day.
You know the swings that we have up out there that we're waiting on the handicapped meetings to come in.
So at the meantime, they kind of wrecked the swings.
So they're going to go by their swings.
You're just packed.
And you know, I'm great.
They're using it.
But I know they're going to be stopped in the mound.
And so the people have been using them.
So we're putting in an extra set of swing sets.
So Kevin's working on getting that together and extending that swing sets.
So we'll have our ADA compliance swing sets, which we're terribly excited about.
And then they'll just move the swing sets that are there over the swings to the new.
What about the outdoor classroom?
Any update on that?
No, at the end, again, I think there's some more of the testing is going to impact that as well.
So they're kind of getting a DQ in and out of the way.
So they can think they're still getting their bids.
And they can be working on a time line.
Good structure.
All right.
Number 20 is Dartmouth.
So move.
Second.
Five.